# Brian D. Baker

brian.baker.bdb@gmail.com 1-440-453-0595

Japanese-English translator/interpreter with skills in programming developed in various projects throughout education and career. Possesses advanced fluency in Japanese from experience living and working in Japan as well as research, analytical, presentation and project management skills honed through graduate school research & teaching duties, translation/interpretation experience, and small-scale software development projects.

### POSITION SOUGHT

Web developer, software developer, or ML/NLP application developer position

## **WORK EXPERIENCE**

In-house Translator/Interpreter, Corporate Commercial Relations

TS Tech Americas, Inc., Reynoldsburg, OH: August 2014 – Present

- Performing simultaneous & consecutive interpretation for sales meetings with customers at the working-level and senior management-level, for internal commercial and manufacturing reviews with senior and executive management, for teleconferences with counterparts in Japan, for biannual business reports to executive leadership, for quarterly executive business management meetings, for new model program milestone reports to executive leadership, for consultation with legal counsel on commercial issues, and for general in-office conversations and discussions between Japanese & English-speaking staff.
- Translating between Japanese & English for sales and sales-engineering presentations to customers, for contracts and legal correspondence, and for internal reports, business plan proposals, and other correspondence.
- Developed MS Office plugins in VBA to accelerate pre- and post-translation formatting. The project was awarded the Technical Merit award at Honda's Fall 2019 CAN Conference.
- Developing machine-learning based system in Python to completely automate pre-translation formatting.
- Managed the adoption of computer-assisted translation technology in corporate purchasing and sales division.

*Graduate Teaching Associate*, Department of East Asian Languages & Literatures The Ohio State University, Columbus, OH; September 2012 – May 2013

- Taught beginner/intermediate Japanese (in individualized and classroom settings), developed and performed lesson plans both for daily performance classes conducted in the Japanese and weekly lectures in English.
- Taught Introduction to East Asian Humanities, performing lectures on topics in China, Korea, and Japan.

Coordinator for International Relations (JET Program), Toyohashi City Hall, Toyohashi, Japan; July 2008 – July 2011

- Translated city government documents and correspondence between Japanese & English.
- Interpreted for delegations from foreign cities meeting with city officials and for English-speaking foreign residents using city hall services.
- Wrote and performed lessons and lectures on American culture for elementary schools and community groups.

*Contract Translator*, *Honda R&D Americas*, *Inc.*, Raymond/East Liberty, OH; July 2007 – January 2008; employed through Next Step Resources

- Performed in-office & teleconference interpretation between Japanese & American staff relating to vehicle durability testing.
- Translated technical documents relating to vehicle durability testing for internal and external use.
- Compiled department spending for internal budget reports.

Contract Translator, American Showa, Inc., Sunbury, OH; May 2007 – July 2007; employed through Next Step Resources

- Provided interpretation between Japanese & English at shock absorber & power steering unit manufacturing plant, primarily for discussions relating to production engineering & quality.
- Translation of engineering-related technical documents and correspondence for internal use.

# Brian D. Baker

brian.baker.bdb@gmail.com 1-440-453-0595

Web Aide, Amherst Exempted Village Schools, Amherst, OH; September 2001 – September 2002

- Designed web pages for elementary, middle, and high school teachers.
- Developed web programs for delivering dynamic content using HTML4, PHP4, & MySQL.

#### **EDUCATION**

Web Development Bootcamp, The Ohio State University, Online. July 2021 – January 2022.

• Covered: Git, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, MERN stack

M.A. in Japanese Linguistics, The Ohio State University, Columbus, OH. September 2011 – August 2014.

• Graduation project: online viewer of Japanese geographical dialect data using JavaScript and Google Maps API v3 for use in dialectology research.

#### 10-Month Intensive Program in Advanced Japanese

Inter-University Center for Japanese Language Studies, Yokohama, Japan. September 2013 – June 2014.

*B.A. in Japanese with Distinction, B.A. in International Studies (International Relations & Diplomacy Specialization) The Ohio State University,* Columbus, OH. September 2002 – March 2007.

Minors: Computer and Information Science, Linguistics. Summa Cum Laude, with Honors in the Arts and Sciences

Year-long Study Abroad Program, University of Tsukuba, Tsukuba, Japan. September 2004 – July 2005.

### **SKILLS**

Languages: English native speaker, fluent in Japanese.

Introductory-level proficiency in Spanish, Korean, and Mandarin Chinese.

Interpretation: Simultaneous & consecutive interpretation between Japanese and English in automotive/manufacturing

on sales, purchasing, manufacturing, development, and business-management subjects. Using and configuring Williams Sound mobile interpreter audio equipment (Digiwave) and

Audio-Technica tabletop discussion system (ATUC-50).

**Translation:** Japanese-to-English & English-to-Japanese in automotive/manufacturing on manufacturing, development,

sales, purchasing, and legal subjects.

Translation with computer-assisted translation software (primarily memoQ).

Computer Programming Tools: HTML, CSS, SQL, JavaScript, XML, Visual Basic for Applications, Regex,

Python (ML libraries: Scikit-learn, TensorFlow 2), Java, Git.

Current Study Interests: Machine learning and natural language processing